Systems and Computing, Office of, Records 1967-1977
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Systems and Computing, Office of, Records
1967-1977
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 58
approximate 1465 items 2.5 linear feet 3 containers
Records include daily correspondence from the office, such as interoffice memoranda, minutes of meetings, office planning information, reports, capital improvement projects and blueprints, research project information, faculty service reports, information on new data processing equipment, etc.
Organizational History:
As early as 1953 a computing laboratory was operating on the campus of Washington State University. The Computing Center was established at the University in 1956; at that time, data-processing projects functioned under the auspices of the Department of Mathematics. The University offered two courses on the subject of computers, taught in the Department of Mathematics, beginning with the 1956-1957 academic year.
In 1966, a "Program in Information Science" was initiated which included vastly expanded course offerings and faculty members. By 1970, the Department of Computer Sciences, with 15 faculty members, had been formed; this program offered M.S. and Ph.D. degrees. During the same time period, the Office of Systems and Computing began operations as a part of the Washington State University administrative body. This office directs all data-processing operations performed for University business, many officials of the office hold joint appointments in the Department of Computer Sciences and the WSU Computing Center.
Currently, the Office of Systems and Computing consists of Computer Engineering Services, Mathematical/Statistical Faculty Consultants, University Computing Services, and the Computing Service Center. The Office, in addition to administering these sub-units, allocates computing funds to the colleges, approves all acquisitions of computer-related equipment, performs long-range planning for WSU computing, and represents WSU to the State Data Processing Authority.
The records of the WSU Office of Systems and Computing are divided into three major series: (1) on-campus correspondence with specific university administrative officers, (2) on-campus correspondence with university administrative offices, and (3) off-campus correspondence. The three correspondence series have been arranged alphabetically by subject: material within each subject is then arranged chronologically. This arrangement is consistent ith the original order as received from the office of Systems and Computing. The records range in date from 1967 to 1977.
The records contain the daily correspondence of the office, which is affiliated with the WSU Computer Sciences Department and reflects all aspects of its operation. The Office of Systems and Computing records contain the following: interoffice and interdepartmental memoranda, office planning information, capital improvement planning and blueprints, reports, technical data, research project information, requests for information from various agencies, minutes of meetings, faculty service reports, departmental and faculty correspondence, information on new data-processing equipment, and other business.
Principal correspondents include William Walden, Wallis Beasley, Warren Bishop, K. Abbey, V. L. Shelton, Allan H. Smith, Glen Terrell, Barry Whelchel, James Quann, and officials of IBM Corporation.
The Collection is open for research use.
The records of the office of Systems and Computing were transferred to the University Archives, Washington State University, in December 1979 (UA 79-28) by the office in accordance with the approved records schedule.
Beasley, Wallis--Archives; Bishop, Warren A.--Archives; Abbey, Kenneth--Archives; Shelton, Vessie Lauren, 1911---Archives; Quann, C. James--Archives; Terrell, William Glenn, 1920---Archives; Smith, Allan H.--Archives; Whelchel, Barry--Archives; Walden, William E.--Archives
Washington State University. Office of Systems and Computing--Archives; International Business Machines Corporation--Archives; Washington State University. Office of Systems and Computing--Records and correspondence; Washington State University--Information technology--History--Archives; Washington State University--Information resources management--History--Archives; International Business Machines Corporation--Records and correspondence
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities
- On-Campus Correspondence--Administrative officers, 1968-1977; 1
  - Beasley, Wallis, 1968-1977; 244 items (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Bishop, Warren and K. Abbey, 1969-1975; 50 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bishop, Warren, 1975-1977; 27 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Shelton, V. L., 1969-1974; 98 items (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Smith, Allan H., 1969-1977; 162 items (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
- On-Campus Correspondence--Administrative Offices, 1967-1977; 2
  - Facilities Planning, 1972-1977; 82 items (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Library, 1967-1973; 34 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - President's Office, 1968-1976; 78 items (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Registrar, 1969-1976; 62 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Staff Personnel, 1969-1977; 132 items (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - General, 1970-1977; 165 items (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
- Off-Campus Correspondence, 1968-1977; 3
  - General, 1970-1977; 263 items (Box 3, Folder 21-28)
  - IBM, 1968-1977; 89 items (Box 3, Folder 29-30)